<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name>Revenant Vampire</name>
        <description>Revenant Vampire Race</description>
        <author>JCDM</author>
        <update version="0.5.08">
            <file name="race_vampire.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/jchezum/items_of_the_sable_cross/master/races/race_vampire.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>

    <element name="Revenant Vampire" type="Race" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACE_VAMPIRE">
        <description>
            <p> 
                Tall, pale and gaunt humanoids, their otherworldly presence and stillness make a vampire stand out among the warm bodied living. 
                With sharp dark facial features, eyes that seem to glow in the absence of light, and cold bodies that cast no reflection, vampires are as solitary as they come.
                Vampires are pale due to their undead nature and avoidance of the sun. While their stillness comes from the fact that they no longer need to draw breath, making every action and 
                inaction a conscious decision on their part. When forced into a corner, their sharp retractable fangs and claws become a declaration of warning to all creatures that bleed as any 
                eloquence in their humanoid guise disappears, replaced with a primal bloodlust as they cut down the living like a plague.
            </p>

            <h4>A Deal Or A Curse</h4>
            <p>
                Undead are not born, and vampires are no exception to this. When a creature dies and rises as a vampire or vampire spawn their race becomes this one, losing their previous traits, ability score increases, etc. 
                Only retaining parts of their physical appearance as their personality is warped into a mockery of their former self. Vampires are usually the result of a dark pact and while the mortal may not make the deal with 
                the goal of becoming a vampire in mind the dark powers they've negotiated with cares little and only seeks to sow as much evil and strife within the world as a result of such a deal. Powerful beings of evil such as 
                malevolent gods are also capable of afflicting a mortal with vampirism.    
            </p>
            <p>
                It is a common misconception that being bitten by a vampire can turn you into one. When in practice it only kills you, warping your body and mind into a an undead monstrosity.  A vampire spawn is often a slave to the 
                true vampire that killed you. It is only by drinking the blood of the vampire that turned you can a vampire spawn then become a vampires. Though, few vampires are willing to relinquish their control in this manner.            
            </p>

            <h4> Coffinlike Structure </h4>
            <p>
                All vampires are bound to a coffinlike structure, normally some form of large container that usually takes the form of a sarcophagus, casket, or coffin. It is here that a vampires rests and reforms when they're defeated. 
                They are usually hidden away in areas that are difficult to access by non-vampires and are heavily protected by minions, traps, and thralls. A coffinlike structure is made from the wood of your original coffin, or the stone 
                of your original tombstone in some cases. The structure is large enough to encase your body in and must have an opening to allow mist to enter and exit. 
                If a vampires didn't receive a formal burial, it must lie beneath a foot of earth at the place of its transition to undeath. A vampires can move its place of burial by transporting its coffinlike structure or a 
                significant amount of grave dirt to another location. Some vampires set up multiple resting places this way.

                With your Dungeon Master's discretion, the area in which your coffinlike structure rests for 2d6 days can be considered your lair, manifesting the following regional effects as it is warped by your unnatural presence:

                There's a noticeable increase in the populations of bats, rats, and wolves in the region.
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Blighted Ground. </i></b>Plants within 500 feet of the lair wither, and their stems and branches become twisted and thorny. </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Ravenous Shadows. </i></b>Shadows cast within 500 feet of the lair seem abnormally gaunt and sometimes move as though alive. </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Grasping Fog. </i></b>A creeping fog clings to the ground within 500 feet of the vampire's lair. The fog occasionally takes eerie forms, such as grasping claws and writhing serpents.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Gaian Recovery. </i></b>If you are destroyed, or you move your coffinlike structure to elsewhere these effects end after 2d6 days. </p>           

            <h4>Vampire Weaknesses</h4>
            <p>
                Although vampires can be incredibly strong, their curse still comes with several notable drawbacks. Regardless of if you are a vampire spawn or a true vampire, you are affected by the following 
                weakness unless specified otherwise:
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Forbiddance: </i></b>You can't enter a residence without an invitation from one of the occupants. </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Running Water: </i></b>Your flesh is torn apart in the presence of water, you take 20 acid damage when you end your turn in running water. This damage may not be reduced in any way.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Stake to the Heart: </i></b>If a piercing weapon made of wood is driven into your heart while incapacitated, you become paralyzed until the stake is removed if you are a true vampire. 
            However, if you are a vampire spawn, you are instead destroyed.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Sunlight Hypersensitivity: </i></b>You sear and burn in the light of the sun, your flesh immolating. If you end your turn in direct sunlight, you take 20 radiant damage. 
            You also have disadvantage on any attack rolls and ability checks when in direct sunlight.</p>

            <h4>VAMPIRE TRAITS</h4>
            <p>Your vampire character has the following traits.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Ability Score Increase. </i></b>Your Strength, Dexterity and Constitution scores each increase by 1.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Age. </i></b>Vampires are immortal and can be any age. Vampires retain the physical appearance of the age at which they were turned at during their mortal life. They also retain the psychological development associated with that age, therefore vampires who did not reach adulthood in their mortal life may still have the impulses of an adolescent in their vampiric life.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Alignment. </i></b>Vampires might not have an innate tendency toward evil, but many of them end up there. Evil or not, their strict hierarchies incline them toward a lawful alignment.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Size. </i></b>Vampire are about the same size and build as humans. Your size is Medium.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Speed. </i></b>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Vampiric Resistance. </i></b>You have resistance to necrotic damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Darkvision.</i></b>Thanks to your heritage, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Undead. </i></b>Your creature type is considered to be both humanoid and undead.</p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Unholy Body. </i></b>
                Dark magic sustains you, making you resistant to necrotic damage. Healing potions do not have a healing effect on you. Instead, they deal poison damage equal to the amount that was meant to heal. 
                To heal you must either drink blood, spend hit dice, or finish a long rest.            
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Blood Drinker. </i></b>
                Even though you are undead, you still require sustenance in the form of blood to sustain your unholy existence. You are immune to diseases. You do not need to eat or breathe, but you can ingest food and drink if 
                you wish, though this food is always bland and stale to you. If you go for longer then seven days without drinking at least one ration of blood, you suffer one level of exhaustion on the midnight of that day, which can 
                only be removed by drinking a ration of blood. After consuming one ration of blood, you recover all levels of exhaustion. If you reach six levels of exhaustion due to this trait, you are destroyed.
                A ration of blood is a vial[1], roughly 4 ounces[2] and while that is just enough to sustain you each week, you still feel the urge to drink and may still appear twitchy or ravenous in the heat of battle or 
                when treating a wounded ally. A pint, such as that contained within a flask[3] is considered a healthy amount, enough to keep you sustained while also suppressing your less civilized behavior. 
                Each ration of blood heals you for 1d4+1 hit points while a pint will heal you for 2d4+2 hit points.
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Bite. </i></b>
                All vampires have sharpened teeth capable of tearing flesh from bone and draining blood from the body.
                If a willing, paralyzed, charmed, incapacitated, restrained, or grappled, creature within 5 feet of you has blood, you may use your bonus action to Bite them dealing 1d6 piercing damage and draining their blood dealing additional necrotic damage equal to your Constitution modifier.
                Drinking blood this way is equal to consuming a ration as per your Blood Drinker trait.
                When you use your Bite, you can choose to not deal damage.            
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Claws. </i></b>
                As a vampire you have a set of claws, your claws are natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes.
                If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength or Dexterity modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.            
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Will of the Master. </i></b>
                You are a vampire spawn and as such your will is circumvented by that of your true vampire master.
                There is little you can do in the way of resisting your master and can't take actions to harm them, however, you can pervert the intent of their commands by exploiting their poor wording.
                The knowing perversion of such a command though will often lead to your destruction if their master believes it to be so.
                Any attempt to go against you masters will or pervert their command requires you to make a DC17 Charisma saving throw at disadvantage.
            </p>
            <p class="indent"><b><i>Languages. </i></b>
                You can speak, read, and write Common, as well as one other language of your choice, that you knew in life. 
            </p>

        </description>
        <sheet display="false" />
        <rules>
            <stat name="strength" value="1" />
            <stat name="dexterity" value="1" />
            <stat name="charisma" value="1" />
            <stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
            <grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
            <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
            <select type="Language" />
            <grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRIC_RESISTANCE" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_BLOODTHIRST" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_CLAWS" />            
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_WILL_OF_THE_MASTER" />     
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_UNDEAD_BODY" />     
        </rules>
    </element>

    <!-- =================================================================================================================================================== -->
    <!-- Racial Traits -->
    <!-- =================================================================================================================================================== -->
    <element name="Vampiric Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRIC_RESISTANCE">
        <description>
            <p>You have resistance to necrotic damage.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You have resistance to necrotic damage.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
		<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_NECROTIC" />
        </rules>
    </element>    
    <element name="Bloodthirst" type="Racial Trait" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_BLOODTHIRST">
        <description>
            <p>
                If a willing, paralyzed, charmed, incapacitated, restrained, or grappled creature within 5 feet of you has blood, you may use your bonus action to Bite them dealing 1d6 piercing damage and draining their blood dealing additional necrotic damage equal to your Constitution modifier.
                Drinking blood this way is equal to consuming a ration as per your Blood Drinker trait.  When you use your Bite, you can choose to not deal damage.              
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                <p>
                    If a willing, paralyzed, charmed, incapacitated, restrained, or grappled creature within 5 feet of you has blood, you may use your bonus action to Bite them dealing 1d6 piercing damage and draining their blood dealing additional necrotic damage equal to your Constitution modifier.
                    Drinking blood this way is equal to consuming a ration as per your Blood Drinker trait.  When you use your Bite, you can choose to not deal damage.              
                </p>            
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>    
    <element name="Claws" type="Racial Trait" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_CLAWS">
        <description>
            <p>
                As a vampire you have a set of claws, your claws are natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes.
                If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength or Dexterity modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.                     
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                <p>
                    As a vampire you have a set of claws (natural weapons), which you can use to make unarmed strikes.
                    If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength or Dexterity modifier.
                </p>            
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>
    <element name="Will of the Master" type="Racial Trait" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_WILL_OF_THE_MASTER">
        <description>
            <p>
                You are a vampire spawn and your will is dominated by that of your true vampire master.
                You cannot resist a direct command from your master, nor can you take actions to harm them.  
                However, you can pervert the intent of their commands by exploiting their poor wording.  This may cause your master to retaliate against you.
                Attempts to go against your master's will or pervert their command requires you to make a Charisma saving throw.
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>
                <p>
                    You are a vampire spawn and your will is dominated by that of your true vampire master.
                    You cannot resist a direct command from your master, nor can you take actions to harm them.  
                    However, you can pervert the intent of their commands by exploiting their poor wording.  This may cause your master to retaliate against you.
                    Attempts to go against your master's will or pervert their command requires you to make a Charisma saving throw.
                </p>            
            </description>
        </sheet>
    </element>   
    <element name="Undead" type="Racial Trait" source="JCDM" id="ID_JCDM_RACIAL_TRAIT_VAMPIRE_UNDEAD_BODY">
        <description>
            <p>Your creature type is considered to be both humanoid and undead.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>Your creature type is considered to be both humanoid and undead.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
		<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_NECROTIC" />
        </rules>
    </element>                 

</elements>